Guide to the Jessie Tarbox Beals Photographs [1900-1940] (Bulk 1904-1920) PR 4
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Series I. Portraits dates from 1900 to approximately 1940. Portrait photographs are filed alphabetically by sitter. Prints of any one sitter with three or more portraits (even if the same image) are filed together. The collection is rich in self-portraits and portraits taken of Beals by others. Beals is shown "on assignment," climbing a 20 foot ladder to get a higher angle at the Louisiana Purchase Exposition, and striding across city streets armed with her camera and tripod. She photographed herself in her studio, and posed often next to her camera.
Series II. Places spans the years from 1902 to 1940 and includes photos of places visited by Beals, as well as her home in New York City. Photos are arranged by state, and thereunder by city or subject. Early photos are of trips to Arkansas and Texas; few of these are captioned. Twenty-nine photos date from the Louisiana Purchase Exposition of 1904. The majority of photos are of Boston, Massachusetts.
Series III. Subjects is comprised of garden and fashion photography. The 25 fashion photos seem to date from Beals' early years in New York, when she was selling photographs to many magazines. The photos are often noted with the name of a store (Gimbels, for example) on the verso. The same models often appear in several different outfits. The garden photos mainly date from after 1927, and are largely of Greenwich Village gardens. A few photos show rooftop gardens, one of which looks out on a river. More than three photos of the same garden are foldered together. One photo shows the tiny back patio of 75 Bedford Street, the "narrowest house in New York." Another shows the gardens of the Rhinelander houses, a group of row houses with wrought iron balconies on West 11th Street, where Beals herself lived from 1936 until her death in 1942.
NOTES ON THE DATABASE AND CATALOGING PROCESS:
Titles for the photos were taken from Beals' written inscriptions found on the versos of many of the prints. Titles in brackets were assigned at the time of processing. The prints in the collection were often made, or inscribed, long after the negative was taken; therefore, stamps of studio addresses on the backs of prints can not be used conclusively to date photos. However, some photos were dated within a general range based on these studio stamps. Other dates were determined based on research conducted on the dates of establishments (i.e. in the case of Greenwich Village tea rooms) or biographies of the subjects. In addition, collections of Beals' work at the Museum of the City of New York and the Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library were consulted for some identification and dating.
Beals had a complex, and sometimes seemingly haphazard, system of numbering her prints. A partial list of these numbers is available in her papers at the Schlesinger Library. Where appropriate, these numbers have been taken into consideration in dating photographs in the collection. Any numbers written on the verso of the photos appear in the database.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
SerIes I. Portraits
Series II. Places
Series III. Subjects
Series IV. Songs of a Wanderer and Other Poetry
Within series, photographs are filed alphabetically by subject when possible.
Related Material at the The New-York Historical Society
Other Greenwich Village scenes at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020), and the Postcard File (PR 054). A copy of Beals's portrait of Mabel Urner Harper is in the Lathrop C. and Mabel H. Urner Harper Collection (PR 121).
The major collection of Beals's photographs, as well as her papers, is held at the Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library at the Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study. Garden photos from that collection are held at the Frances Loeb Library at Harvard University. The Rare Books and Manuscript Library at Columbia University holds the Community Service Society Papers, which include many Beals photos of New York City street children. Forty-five items, primarily Greenwich Village postcards and other scenes of New York City, are at the Museum of the City of New York.
Allen, Viola, 1867-1948--Portraits; Anderson, Judith, Dame, 1898- -- Portraits; Auslander, Joseph, 1897- -- Portraits; Beals, Jessie Tarbox; Beckwith, J. Carroll (James Carroll), 1852-1917 -- Portraits; Bitter, Karl Theodore Francis, 1867-1915 -- Portraits; Borglum, Gutzon, 1867-1941 -- Portraits; Borglum, Solon Hannibal, 1868-1922 -- Portraits; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933 -- Portraits; Dell, Floyd, 1887-1969 -- Portraits; Fisher, Harrison, 1875-1934 -- Portraits; Fokine, Michel, 1880-1942 -- Portraits; French, Daniel Chester, 1850-1931 -- Portraits; Geddes, Norman Bel, 1893-1958 -- Portraits; Hartmann, Sadakichi, 1867-1944 -- Portraits; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964 -- Portraits; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920 -- Portraits; Hurst, Fannie, 1889-1968 -- Portraits; Keyes, Frances Parkinson, 1885-1970 -- Portraits; Louisiana Purchase Exposition (1904: Saint Louis, Mo.) -- Pictorial works; MacDowell, Marian, 1857-1956 -- Portraits; Massachusetts State House (Boston, Mass.) -- Pictorial works; Maule, Frances, 1879-1966 -- Portraits; Museum of Fine Arts, Boston -- Pictorial works; O'Neill, Rose Cecil, 1874-1944 -- Portraits; Old South Church (Boston, Mass.) -- Pictorial works; Post, Emily, 1873-1960 -- Portraits; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967 -- Portraits; Sarg, Tony, 1882-1942 -- Portraits; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930 -- Portraits; Tarbell, Ida M. (Ida Minerva), 1857-1944 -- Portraits; Tarkington, Booth, 1869-1946 -- Portraits; Teasdale, Sara, 1884-1933 -- Portraits; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910 -- Portraits; Urner, Mabel Herbert, 1881-1957 -- Portraits; Vonnoh, Bessie Potter, 1872-1955 -- Portraits; Weir, Julian Alden, 1852-1919 -- Portraits; Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith, 1856-1923 -- Portraits; Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1850-1919 -- Portraits; Wiles, Irving Ramsay, 1861-1948 -- Portraits; Woolworth Building (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Actors -- Portraits; Actresses -- Portraits; Architecture, Domestic -- United States -- Pictorial works; Arkansas -- Pictorial works; Artists -- Portraits; Authors -- Portraits; Boston (Mass.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Fashion photographs; Gardens -- United States -- Pictorial works; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909 -- Pictorial works; Nantucket (Mass.) -- Pictorial works; Photographic postcards; Photographic prints; Portraits; Postcards; Robert Gould Shaw Memorial (Boston, Mass.) -- Pictorial works; Saint Louis (Mo.) -- Pictorial works; San Antonio (Tex.) -- Pictorial works; Self-portraits; Street photography
- Series I. Portraits
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Portraits dates from 1900 to approximately 1940. The collection is rich in self-portraits and portraits taken of Beals by others. Beals is shown "on assignment," climbing a 20 foot ladder to get a higher angle at the Louisiana Purchase Exposition, and striding across city streets armed with her camera and tripod. She photographed herself in her studio, and posed often next to her camera. One photo shows her with naturalist John Burroughs.
  Most portraits seem to have been taken in New York City, often at Beals' many studios. A few portraits, such as those of Booth Tarkington, Ernest Thompson Seton and Grace Seton-Thompson, William Faversham, Joseph Lincoln, and William Dean Howells, show the sitter in his or her country home. Portraits of artists include Jonas Lie, Boardman Robinson, May Wilson Preston, Rose O'Neill Wilson, Irving Wiles, James Carroll Beckwith, and Ernest Thompson Seton. Sculptors include Gutzon and Solon Borglum, Karl Bitter, Paul Trubetzkoi, Bessie Potter Vonnoh, and Daniel Chester French. Cartoonists Fontaine Fox, Homer Davenport, and John McCutcheon are also shown. Portraits also include Norman Bel Geddes, set and costume designer, and puppeteer Tony Sarg.
  Writers pictured include Fannie Hurst, Llewelyn Powys and Alyse Gregory, Kate Douglas Wiggin, Emily Post, Grace Duffie Boylan, William Allen White, Ida Tarbell, and Albert Payson Terhune. Critic Sadakichi Hartman and poet and biographer Carl Sandburg are pictured. Portraits include poets Margaret Widdemer, Joseph Auslander and Sara Teasdale. Actors and actresses of both stage and screen are pictured, such as Judith Anderson, Leonore Ulrich, William Faversham, and Albert Herter. Playwrights Zoe Aiken and Rachel Crothers are also included.
  Greenwich Village inhabitants and celebrities include Edith Unger, proprietress of the Mad Hatter Tea Room, writer Floyd Dell, restaurateur Alice Foote MacDougall, and actor Jerry Norris. More Greenwich Village bohemians can be found in Series II, in the Greenwich Village photos.
  Many portraits in the collection show people not involved in the arts. Pioneering women doctors Mary Walker and Josephine Baker are shown, as are politicians W. H. Woodin and William McAdoo. Presidents William Taft, Calvin Coolidge, and Herbert Hoover are pictured. Seemingly 'everyday people' like Capt. Billy Bowen, a sea captain, and Jane Deeter Rippin, director of a Girl Scout camp, are also pictured. Auctioneer John Mitchell is shown in full swing at a Conneticut auction. Chauncey Messenger, a beekeeper, was photographed peering out from his beehouse.
  Portraits are arranged alphabetically by sitter. Sitters with three or more portraits (even if the same image) were issued their own folder.
  - "A-B" general, including: Akins, Zoe Allen, Viola Anderson, Judith Andrews, Kenneth Auslander, Joseph Baker, Sara Josephine Beals, Alfred Tennyson (See: Box 1, folder 2) Beckwith, James Carroll Blasco Ibanez, Vicente Borglum, Gutzon Borglum, Solon Hannibal Bowen, Billy Brainerd, Nanette Beals Brandstrom, Elsa Burroughs, John (See: Box 1, folder 2) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Beals, Jessie Tarbox, 1904-[1920], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
    See also: Box 4, folder 36
  - Bitter, Karl Theodore Francis, 1906-[1915] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Boylan, Grace Duffie and Malcolm Stuart, [1905-17] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "C-E" general, including: Chamberlin, Frank Tolles Cone, Sylvanus Coolidge, Calvin Coolidge, Grace Goodhue and Frances Parkinson Keyes Cooper, Colin Campbell Crothers, Rachel Davenport, Homer Dawson, Coningsby Dean, Walter Lofthouse (See: Box 3, Folder 22) Dell, Floyd Doro, Marie Dunbar, Charles Edson, Myra Durr (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "F-G" general, including: Farnham, Sally James Farquhan, Sam Faversham, William Fenn, Harry Finley, John Huston Fisher, Harrison Fokine, Michel Fokina, Vera Petrovna Fox, Fontaine French, Daniel Chester Gelber, Walter Girard, Madame Gregory, Alyse (See: Box 2, Folder 15) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Geddes, Norman Bel, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "H-K" general, including: Hartmann, Sadakichi Haviland, Anne Herter, Albert Holder, Mary Hoover, Herbert Hoover, Lou Henry Horne, Mrs. Greenwich Hurst, Fannie James, Helen Field Keene, Doris Kelly, Alice McKay Keyes, Frances Parkinson (See: Box 1, Folder 5) King, Helen Kronold, Hans (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Howells, William Dean, [1908] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "L-M" general, including: Lane, Winifred Letson, Ely [?] Lincoln, Joseph Crosby Lipton, Thomas Johnstone, Sir Logan, Josephine Hancock MacDougall, Alice Foote (See also: Box 4, Folder 38) MacDowell, Marian Mann, Mme Martin, Jane Maule, Frances McAdoo, William Gibbs McCutcheon, John Tinney Messenger, Chauncey Moore, Mary Morgan, Pauline (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lie, Jonas, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mitchell, John W., 1937 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "N-R" general, including: Netcher, Charles, Mrs. Norris, Jean Norris, Jerry O'Neill, Rose Cecil Oyen, Henry Peters, Rollo Post, Emily Potter, Grace Powell, Charlotte Preston, May Wilson Raoul, William Greene Rehber, Helen Rippin, Jane Deeter Rives, Amelie Roberts, Charles George Robinson, Boardman (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pomeroy, Bill, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Powys, Llewelyn, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "S-T" general, including: Sanborn, Kate Sandburg, Carl Sennett, Charley Seton, Ernest Thompson Seton-Thompson, Grace Gallatin Seton, Anya Simpson, Jerry Starr, Frances Stevens, Alice Swanson, Valette [?] Tarbell, Ida Minerva Tarkington, Booth Teasdale, Sara Terhune, Albert Payson Tolerton, H. H. Trubetskoi, Pavel Petrovich, kniaz' Truex, Ernest Twain, Mark (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sarg, Tony, [1939] (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Taft, William H., [1908-12] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "U-Wh" general, including: Unger, Edith Vinton, Frederick Porter Volpi, Countess Vonnoh, Bessie Potter Wade, Alzirc Hewitt, Mrs. Walker, Mary Edwards Watson, Dudley Crafts Weir, Julian Alden Wenzell, Albert Beck White, William Allen (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Ulrich, Leonore, [1915-28] (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Urner, Mabel Herbert, [1905-27] (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Wi-Z" general, including: Widdemer, Margaret (See also: Box 6, Folder 53) Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith (See: Box 6, Folder 53) Wilcox, Ella Wheeler Wiles, Irving Ramsay Willet, Frank Wilmut, Millicent Woodin, W. Hugh Yates, Cullen and Walter Lofthouse Dean Young, Mary Young, Roland (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series II: Places
  Series II spans the years from 1902 to 1940 and includes photos of places visited by Beals, as well as her home in New York City. Photos are arranged by state, and thereunder by city or subject. Early photos are of trips to Arkansas and Texas; few of these are captioned. Twenty-nine photos date from the Louisiana Purchase Exposition of 1904.
  The photographs of Boston appear to have been taken between 1902 and 1910. Most Boston views are of popular tourist sites, such as the Boston Common, the Shaw Memorial, the Massachusetts State House, and the Park Street Church. Many are taken in winter, specifically in or after snowstorms. A few photos were artistically mounted on larger paper, with Beals signature and studio location written at the lower right of the photo. Many of these are reprints dating from the early 1930s, when Beals was living in Chicago and trying to sell her older photographs to a new audience.
  Although Beals took over 5,000 photographs of every aspect of the Louisiana Purchase Exposition, the group held in this collection focuses on the airshow competition in the fall of 1904. Three of the four prime competitors, Thomas Baldwin's "California Arrow," Francois' "Ville de St. Mande," and Thomas Benbow's "Montana Meteor," are shown. These early aircraft are seen in flight or tethered to the ground and surrounded by onlookers. One photo shows Beals herself seated on the pilot's platform of the "Ville de St. Mande." Pilots William Avery, Thomas Baldwin, and Roy Knabenshue are shown with their aircrafts, and the fair's Governor, Benjamin B. Odell, is shown in the transportation building.
  The New York scenes are generally of lower Manhattan, including the Woolworth Building, City Hall and the Municipal Building, and the New York Stock Exchange. They also include a view of the New York Public Library on 42nd Street, and a view of a suffrage rally in Union Square. Most New York photographs are of Greenwich Village and of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration held in the fall of 1909.
  The photos of Greenwich Village generally show establishments frequented by bohemians. Often the proprietors of these shops are shown in their element. More formal portraits of some Greenwich Village bohemians can be found in Series I. Those pictured in this series include: Romayne Benjamin, Bobby Edwards, Tiny Tim (Timothy Felter), Grace Godwin, Ami Mali Hicks, Adele Kennedy, Elizabeth Koenig, Romany Marie (Marie Marchand), and Kitty Morton. Street scenes show small streets such as Christopher Street, MacDougal Alley, and Patchin Place, a small court off 11th Street where many bohemians lived during the teens.
  The postcards of Greenwich Village are remarkable in that they show images which Beals intended for sale, and which did, in fact, sell to tourists, and undoubtedly to residents of the Village as well. Villagers grumbled about the increased commercialization of their neighborhood after the war, but they were as self-promotional as Beals. Several of these postcards have Beals' humorous verses about the people or places illustrated. The Village was a remarkably fluid place, and establishments often had several incarnations over the years. One example in these photographs is Beals' own Village Art Gallery, which went on to become the Crumperie, a tea room.
  The photos of the Hudson-Fulton Celebration were sold to the Celebration Commission by Beals. Her numbers appear on the backs, but other numbers appear attached to the front, perhaps indicating that the photos had been removed from an album. The photos focus on the historical parade held in Manhattan, but also show the fleet being welcomed upriver at Newburgh with a "living flag" of people attired in red, white, and blue.
  Images are arranged by state and thereunder by subject.
  - Arkansas
    - General Views, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Massachusetts-Boston
    - General Views, [1902-10] (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Boston Common, [1902-10] (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Chestnut Street, [1902-10] (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Custom House, [1902-10] (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Louisburg Square, [1902-10] (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Museum of Fine Arts, [1902-10] (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Old South Church, [1902-10] (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Park Street Church, [1902-10] (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Shaw Memorial, [1902-10] (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - State House, [1902-10] (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Woman's City Club, [1902-10] (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Massachusetts--Nantucket
    See: Box 6
  - Missouri--St. Louis
    - Louisiana Purchase Exposition, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - New York--New York
    - General views, [1905-40] (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Greenwich Village--General views, [1905-20] (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Greenwich Village--Grace Godwin's Garrett, [1917-18] (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Greenwich Village--Parades and productions, [1915-18] (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Greenwich Village--Postcards, [1905-20], undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Greenwich Village--Street scenes, [1905-20], undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
      See also: Box 6, Folder 55
    - Hudson-Fulton Celebration, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Texas--San Antonio
    - Farmhouse, [1905] (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Unidentified/Miscellaneous
    - Unidentified, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 45)
- Series III: Subjects
  Series III is comprised of garden and fashion photography. The 25 fashion photos seem to date from Beals' early years in New York, when she was selling photographs to many magazines. The photos are often noted with the name of a store (Gimbels, for example) on the verso. The same models often appear in several different outfits. The garden photos mainly date from after 1927, and are largely of Greenwich Village gardens. A few photos show rooftop gardens, one of which looks out on a river. More than three photos of the same garden are foldered together. One photo shows the tiny back patio of 75 Bedford Street, the "narrowest house in New York." Another shows the gardens of the Rhinelander houses, a group of row houses with wrought iron balconies on West 11th Street, where Beals herself lived from 1936 until her death in 1942.
  - Fashion Photography
    - General fashion photography, [1905-18] (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - "The right way to.. ." series, [1905-18] (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Garden Photography
    - General garden photography, [1905-40], undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Garden of Mrs. Regina Jais, New York City, [1936-37] (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Garden of Mr. and Mrs. John Morgan, New York City, [1938-40] (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Garden of George and Mary Stonehill, New York City, [1936-37] (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Garden of Mr. and Mrs. W. H. Wells, New York City, 1936, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
- Oversize Materials
  - From Series I. Portraits
    - Wi-Z miscellaneous, including: Widdemer, Margaret (See also: Box 3, Folder 22) Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith, [1900], undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - From Series II. Places
    - Massachusetts--Nantucket--General view, [1905-15] (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - New York--New York--Greenwich Village--Street scene, [1905-20] (Box 6, Folder 55)
- Series IV. Songs of a Wanderer and Other Poetry, 1924, 1928, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes a copy of Songs of a Wanderer, Jessie Tarbox Beals's collection of her poetry (1928). This copy includes an inscription by Beals on the opening pages and another to Mary Dear on the poem "Doreen," on page 50. The series also includes three standalone poems by Beals: "The Hell Ye Can't," "Nothing Matters Long" (inscribed for Mary) and an untitled poem in the shape of a Christmas tree (1924). The donor's great-aunt, Mary Johnson, originally of Kilkenny, Ireland, lived in Greenwich Village and is believed by him to be the Mary referenced in Beals's inscriptions.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
  Gift of Michael P. Johnson, March 2012.